Okay, so today's דף daf is קב. Kuf-Bet. And we have been
talking about this issue of if שינוי מקום צריך לברך, shinui makom
tzrich l'varech, if one changes locations and you have to make another
ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona. It started specifically with the issue of wine,
you made a קידוש Kiddush in one place, you said בורא פרי
הגפן, borei pri hagafen, you drank, let's even say it was מקום
סעודה, makom seudah, and then you went and you wanted to continue
drinking somewhere else. Do you have to make another ברכה, bracha, which
is a general ברכות brachot question, less of a פסחים Pesachim question?
And there there were different opinions. רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both
said you had to make another בורא פרי הגפן. borei pri hagafen.
רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan said you did not. We had a proof
from a ברייתא braita against רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan that said שינוי
מקום צריך לברך, shinui makom tzrich l'varech, you have to. And then
the גמרא Gemara made a distinction, had a debate between רב ששת
Rav Sheshet and רב הונא. Rav Huna. רב הונא Rav Huna said
that you would only have to make another ברכה bracha if in
the new place, if you were not having in the first place
a meal that required a ברכה bracha in the same location, a
ברכה אחרונה, bracha achrona, like בענטשינג, bentching, or על המחיה Al Hamichya
according to most. Then in that, if that were the case that
you were having a meal that required a ברכה bracha at the
end in the same place, then even if you went, somewhat ironically,
even if you went to a different place and continued drinking, it's
not considered a new experience. It's considered all, anyway you're allowed to
come back to your old place to בענטש bentch anyway, and it's
all considered an extension of the primary eating that was done in
the first place. And in that case you do not require a
new ברכה. bracha. That was רב הונא's Rav Huna position as opposed
to under other scenarios you would when you switch places. And רב
ששת Rav Sheshet says regardless when you switch places you have to
make another ברכה. bracha. And the גמרא Gemara then had a proof
in a scenario that was not exactly identical, that was you switched
places and you came back. That's a case where you might think
that everybody says you don't have to make a new one, but
nevertheless the גמרא Gemara treated it as the same. And the case
was that people were sitting and they were drinking wine and presumably
as the גמרא Gemara assumes they were eating a meal. And then
they went out to go to שול shul or they went out
for חתן וכלה, chatan v'kallah, and when they come back do they
have to make a new ברכה bracha or not? So the ברייתא
braita says they don't have to make a new ברכה bracha if
they left people behind. So גמרא Gemara says look, it sounds like,
A, it sounds like that says that they had uprooted themselves, sounds
like they were having a serious meal there, like המוציא, Hamotzi, and
nevertheless the only reason they don't make a new ברכה bracha is
because they left people behind. So it sounds like against רב הונא,
Rav Huna, it sounds like under other circumstances you would always have
to make a new ברכה bracha once you switch locations even if
you were having bread and even as this ברייתא braita seems to
say, even if you returned to the original place. So that's where
we left off where the evidence of this ברייתא braita seems to
be that you have to make a new ברכה bracha once you
switch locations even in a case where you were having a real
fixed meal in the original location. Joe, you had a question?
The entire discussion as you've just summarized is very much organized around
the objectivity of place. Like in this place, right in that place.
I see תוספות Tosafot at the bottom of עמוד ב, amud bet,
קב עמוד ב, Kuf-Bet amud bet, introduces היסח הדעת hessech hadaat which
is that subjective category.
We
haven't raised that in this discussion at all. Is that something the
ראשונים Rishonim introduce into this, like there's this subjective element?
Yes, there is. And the phrase that you find in often in
the ראשונים Rishonim and in another תוספות Tosafot is that part of
this position is that שינוי מקום shinui makom constitutes היסח הדעת hessech
hadaat by definition, which means you could interpret it as meaning we
assume
you're מסיח דעת masiach daat when you switch locations on the fact
that you're eating. Like you lose the mindset of eating and therefore
when you decide to eat again it's a new
experience. I understand which is why it seems more accurate anyway to
read it as it's an objective counterpart to היסח הדעת. hessech hadaat.
The same way היסח הדעת hessech hadaat creates a sense of discontinuity,
so שינוי מקום shinui makom also creates this objective sense of discontinuity.
But not that we're trying to argue that it really is a
proof of or an indicator of an actual subjective היסח הדעת. hessech
hadaat. Look, reality is הלכה halacha anyway prefers objective measures than invisible
subjective ones. So that seems to be the concern here. The גמרא
Gemara does not mention היסח הדעת. hessech hadaat.
In fact, if you stay in the same place and you fall
asleep, exactly,
so there you might
be מסיח דעת. masiach daat. Or you went to watch the football
game and then you completely forgot about your meal and then you
wanted to go back and continue eating. So the היסח הדעת hessech
hadaat is a subjective reality of a discontinuity with your eating. And
the שינוי מקום, shinui makom, the issue seems to be more of
an objective one which is why, again, more formal and objective criteria
like were you קובע סעודה koveia seudah in this place might be
able to come and assist because then it says things are seen
more easily as an
extension. So there might be a difference there, but there is some
actual discussion that even if you're continuing to eat, שינוי מקום shinuy
makom might require a ברכה. bracha.
Now, not washing your hands again.
Now again, no, well okay, but let I'm not going into all
the הלכה, halacha, but I do want to point out just as
a tie-in to Dov's point is that the question is to what
degree does specific intent overcome the issues of שינוי מקום? shinuy makom?
And תוספות Tosafot does discuss for example by קידוש במקום סעודה, Kiddush
bimkom seudah, תוספות Tosafot discusses a middle a middle place of not
מקום makom is, you know, the roof and the floor of the
same building, where תוספות Tosafot said there if you have it in
mind it constitutes one place.
This means to go to the roof, to go
from the roof to the floor, to go from inside to outside
having it in mind won't help, and different spaces in the same
room you don't need to have it in mind, but in this
middle type of of of scenario it would. So you could ask
this question by by שינוי מקום shinuy makom as well, the inter
the intersection between the subjective intent and the objective reality, to what
degree can positive subjective intent help? But let's move on. So the
גמרא Gemara says we'll read the last line of ק"א עמוד ב'.
Kuf Aleph Amud Bais. So קשיא לרב חסדא, kashya l'Rav Chisda,
so this ברייתא braita that I just said to you about uprooting
and coming back, it sounded like they were having a fixed meal,
and it sounded like with if they didn't leave anybody behind, they'd
have to make a new ברכה bracha when they returned. So that's
against רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, and this is even when they came
back to the same place. So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, so רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak will tell you top of ק"ב עמוד א', Kuf Bais Amud
Aleph, מאן תנא עקירות רבי יהודה. man tanna akiros Rabbi Yehuda. No,
no, no. Who is the author of that ברייתא braita about uprooting
yourself and leaving people behind? That's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. But there's
going to be a חכמים, Chachamim, a majority opinion that argues on
him that says that you don't have to make another ברכה. bracha.
דתניא, detanya, we taught in the ברייתא. braita.
חברים שהיו מסובין, chaverim shehayu mesubin, so this is almost exactly the
same as the ברייתא braita we just read, the first part about
it at least, or the whatever the second part about it. חברים
שהיו מסובין, chaverim shehayu mesubin, if a group that were reclining and
basically means that they were having a meal. So that's דברים טעונים
ברכה אחריהם במקומם, devarim teunim bracha achareihem bimkomam, something that you would
have to go back and make a and make a benching in
that place.
Not on Shabbos?
No, no, no, no, yeah, during on a Wednesday. ועקרו רגליהם לילך
לבית הכנסת או לבית המדרש, v'akru ragleihem leilech l'beis haknesses o l'beis
hamidrash,
and then they got up in order to go to shul or
to go to the study hall. כשהן יוצאין אין טעונין ברכה למפרע,
keshen yotzin ein teunim bracha l'mafrea, when they leave they don't have
to make a ברכה bracha you know on what they had already
eaten. וכשהן חוזרין אין טעונין ברכה לכתחילה, u'cheshen chozrin ein teunim bracha
l'chatchila, and when they because they're planning on coming back, so don't
bother benching now, don't worry, you'll come back, and when you come
back you don't have to make a new המוציא, Hamotzi, and then
you'll just finish eating and then you'll make a ברכה bracha at
the end. Now, אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, by the way
some of the ראשונים Rishonim point out that the חידוש chiddush of
אין טעון ברכה למפרע ein taun bracha l'mafrea is also that we're
not concerned that you might come to forget that you might forget
to come back. So maybe we would say yes, if you do
come back you won't have to bench again, but maybe we would
insist you bench before you leave cause you might forget to come
back. Okay? But I guess but but anyway so that's how they
understand part of the חידוש. chiddush. But either way we see you
don't have to make either a benching or a new ברכה ראשונה
bracha rishona when you return. אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, said
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, במה דברים אמורים, bameh
devarim amurim, when is that true? בזמן שהניחו שם מקצת חברים, bizman
shehinichu sham miktzas chaverim, if they left some people behind. אבל לא
הניחו שם מקצת חברים, aval lo hinichu sham miktzas chaverim, if they
didn't leave people behind, כשהן יוצאין טעונין ברכה למפרע, keshen yotzin teunim
bracha l'mafrea,
when they leave they do have to make a ברכת המזון. Birkas
HaMazon. וכשהן חוזרין טעונין ברכה לכתחילה, u'cheshen chozrin teunim bracha l'chatchila, they
do have to make a new המוציא. Hamotzi. So you so yes,
is there an opinion that says that they do have to make
a new ברכה? bracha? Yes, that's the position of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda if nobody is left behind. But the חכמים Chachamim say that
even if nobody is left behind, they don't have to make a
new ברכה. bracha. So that is consistent with רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
that is consistent with the idea that as long as you had
a place where you were really having a סעודה, seudah, a שינוי
מקום shinuy makom does not require a new ברכה. bracha. Now again,
that's in a scenario where you returned, but at least it's not
a contradiction to רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. It's only רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda that insists on a new ברכה. bracha. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara does with it. So the גמרא Gemara says okay
where were we? אלא טעמא, ela taama, so the גמרא Gemara says
okay so what have you shown? דבדברים הטעונים ברכה לאחריהם במקומן, d'bidvarim
hateunim bracha l'achareihem bimkoman, so the reason now that you've explained this
ברייתא braita is the חכמים Chachamim who argue on רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda that say you don't need a new ברכה bracha is that
things that require ברכה bracha in that a ברכה אחרונה bracha achrona
in that same place meaning like benching, that's why כשהן יוצאין אין
טעונין ברכה למפרע כשהן חוזרין אין טעונין ברכה לכתחילה. keshen yotzin ein
teunim bracha l'mafrea keshen chozrin ein teunim bracha l'chatchila. That's why when
they return they don't have to make a new ברכה bracha because
they're returning to their קביעותא קמא keviusa kama to where they had
originally established their meal and the שינוי מקום shinuy makom doesn't interrupt
it. So the implication though would be אבל דברים שאין טעונין ברכה
לאחריהם במקומן, aval devarim she'ein teunim bracha l'achareihem bimkoman, if it was
not something that requires עקירה. akira. It wasn't that they like established
a meal. It was something that didn't require a ברכה bracha afterwards
in the same place like they were just סתם stam drinking wine
or they were having meat or whatever it wasn't like המוציא. hamotzi.
So if it was a scenario that was not as to the
same degree, in that case the implication of this ברייתא baraita is
that אפילו רבנן afilu rabanan that even the Rabbis who argue on
רב יהודה Reb Yehuda would say כשהן יוצאין טעונין ברכה למפרע וכשהן
חוזרין טעונין ברכה לכתחילה keshen yotzin te'unin bracha lemafrei'a u-keshen chozrin te'unin
bracha lechatchila that they would have to make a ברכה אחרונה bracha
achrona and they would have to make a new ברכה ראשונה. bracha
rishona. So okay what's the problem with that? I mean what the
גמרא Gemara said is again the scenario is the גמרא Gemara understands
the ברייתא baraita a group of people are having some bread, they're
having a meal, they leave, they make a, when they come back
according to the חכמים Chachamim they don't have to make a, they
don't have to בענטש, bench, they don't have to make a new
ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona. Okay, that is the חכמים Chachamim who argue
on רב יהודה Reb Yehuda it doesn't matter that they left people
behind. So the גמרא Gemara is saying is fine, presumably though the
reason is because you set up the scenario that they were having
a meal, that they were having like המוציא. hamotzi. In another scenario
if they left and came back or you know they would have
to make a new ברכה. bracha. So the basic implication of this
ברייתא baraita is that generally שינוי מקום shinnuy makom requires a new
ברכה. bracha. The reason it doesn't require a new ברכה bracha in
this case according to the חכמים Chachamim is because it was a
case of עקרו akru that they were having a fixed meal, they
had a סעודה se'uda and then they had, they got up. But
if they weren't a סעודה se'uda a normal שינוי מקום shinnuy makom
would require a ברכה. bracha. Okay, what's the problem with that? That's
what we've been saying all along, that a normal שינוי מקום shinnuy
makom requires a ברכה. bracha. So the גמרא Gemara says well let's
see where the גמרא Gemara is going with this. The גמרא Gemara
says לימא תהוי תיובתא דרבי יוחנן leima teheve tiyuvta de-Rabbi Yochanan so
this should be a contradiction to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan because רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said yesterday that שינוי מקום shinnuy makom never requires
a new ברכה. bracha. So this ברייתא baraita seems to be a
proof against him because this ברייתא baraita seems to say the only
reason it doesn't require a new ברכה bracha is because it was
a scenario that they were מסובין mesubin that they were, had a
fixed meal. But under other cases changing locations would require. So this
seems to be a contradiction to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who says
it never requires. So the גמרא Gemara says ולאו אותביה חדא זימנא
ve-lav motviyah chada zimna who needs a contradiction to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, didn't we already contradict רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan earlier? If you
remember yesterday it said תיובתא דרבי יוחנן תיובתא. tiyuvta de-Rabbi Yochanan tiyuvta.
Right? We showed that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was directly contradicted that
you do need a new ברכה bracha when you switch places. Okay
yes that's implied in this ברייתא baraita too, big deal. So the
גמרא Gemara says לימא מהא נמי תהוי תיובתא. leima me-ha nami teheve
tiyuvta. Okay but you know maybe if once is good twice is
better right? Let's heap it on. Can we say that this ברייתא
baraita as well contradicts רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? Now the ראשונים Rishonim
say why do we need to you know to beat him up
but it's saying because you know just if you have one proof
against someone although the גמרא Gemara there did say it's an absolute
contradiction maybe somebody'll find a way out of it, maybe you'll find
out it's a corrupt text. The more proof that you can have
the more definite your position will be that we reject רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. So this רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who says that you
never have to make a new ברכה. bracha. So this ברייתא baraita
again assumes you don't make a new ברכה bracha when you return
but it sounds like only because they were having a סעודה. se'uda.
If that was not the case they would, does this seem to
be another contradiction to רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? Let's read the answer.
אמר לך רבי יוחנן amar lecha Rabbi Yochanan רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
could tell you no, הוא הדין אפילו דברים שאין טעונין ברכה לאחריהן
במקומן נמי אין צריכין לברך. hu hadin afilu devarim she-ein te'unin bracha
le'achareihen bimkoman nami ein tzerichin levareich. You know what? The חכמים Chachamim
that say when you return you don't have to make a new
ברכה bracha they would say whatever you were eating, even if you
weren't eating bread, you never have to make a new ברכה bracha
just because of שינוי מקום. shinnuy makom. והא דקתני עקרו רגליהם ve-ha
de-ktani akru ragleihem so why did it say they uprooted themselves? Why
did it have to use that phrase which suggests that we're talking
only in a case where they're having a קביעת סעודה kevi'at se'uda
where they're really planting themselves in their place initially to have a
fixed meal? Why do we use that phrase if it's true that
you never have to make a new ברכה? bracha? להודיעך כוחו דרבי
יהודה le-hodi'acha kocho de-Reb Yehuda because then it tells you the חידוש
chiddush about how מחמיר machmir רב יהודה Reb Yehuda is. רב יהודה
Reb Yehuda says that without leaving people behind you have to make
a new ברכה. bracha. דאפילו דברים שטעונין ברכה לאחריהן במקומן de-afilu devarim
she-te'unin bracha le'achareihen bimkoman even a case where you do have to,
it is like a meal where you would have to make בענטשן
bentshen in that place where you had bread, where you were קובע
סעודה. kovei'a se'uda. Even in those scenarios the טעמא ta'ama the only
way רב יהודה Reb Yehuda gets you out of it is דהניחו
מקצת חברים de-hinihu miktzat chaverim only when some people were left behind.
אבל לא הניחו מקצת חברים aval lo hinihu miktzat chaverim when people
weren't left behind כשהן יוצאין טעונין ברכה למפרע וכשהן חוזרין טעונין ברכה
לכתחילה. keshen yotzin te'unin bracha lemafrei'a u-keshen chozrin te'unin bracha lechatchila. In
that case you would always have to make a new ברכה. bracha.
So again to repeat the scenarios we've got, okay? I think this
is getting just a little bit confusing. Oh look we have company.
What? Yeah, yeah. So anyway so of course so רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says do you have to make a new ברכה bracha when
you have שינוי מקום? shinnuy makom? He says never. Okay and here
you have רב הונא Rav Huna and רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. So
they say they say yes you do have to make a new
ברכה bracha but רב ששת Rav Sheshet says always and רב הונא
Rav Huna says only. If, you know, not סעודה seudah *se'udah*, you
know המוציא Hamotzi? *Hamotzi*, okay, המוציא *Hamotzi* or מזונות *Mezonos*. But if
it was המוציא *Hamotzi* or מזונות *Mezonos*, then you do then you
do not have to make a new ברכה bracha *berachah*. Okay, those
are the different range of opinions. We had already had a ברייתא
baraita. *braita* we said that רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* we had contradicted
him. Okay, now we have this case, right, which is the people
that you have the, the things that you have the friends. Here's
all these people sitting and eating. Okay, okay, there's the loaf of
bread. All right, and they have to get up and they go
to, to חתן וכלה chatan vekallah? *chassan v'kallah*, right? So that's the
case, that's the ברייתא Baraisa: *braita* that we have. So רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* says that normally if they didn't leave people behind, right,
no one left behind. Who's that? No one left behind, no child
left behind. But no one is left behind, so רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* says you have to make a ברכה bracha? *berachah* and the
חכמים *Chachamim* say you don't. Okay, you don't. Okay, so we're assuming
that we're talking that it was a סעודה *se'udah*. So how does
this work? So basically you see, look, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says
you do make a ברכה bracha *berachah*, that's basically similar to רב
ששת Rav Sheshet, *Rav Sheshet*, right? רב Rav. ששת *Rav Sheshet* says
you always make a, you always make a new ברכה bracha, *berachah*.
The חכמים *Chachamim* say you don't, but that works with רב Rav
הונא *Rav Huna* because here you're having a סעודה *se'udah*, so if
you're having a סעודה *se'udah*, so you do not have to, right?
רב Rav הונא *Rav Huna* says if you have a סעודה *se'udah*,
then no. Okay, so that's how he sort of fixed out the
ברייתא *braita*. That look, the חכמים *Chachamim* disagree with רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda*, the חכמים *Chachamim* say you don't need it, it's because you're
having a סעודה *se'udah*, so that's consistent with רב Rav הונא *Rav
Huna* who says that when you're having a סעודה *se'udah* you don't
have to make a new ברכה *berachah*. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
says okay, but everybody basically here seems to say that if you
weren't having a סעודה *se'udah*, if it wasn't a special case, then
presumably everybody would say you have to make a new ברכה *berachah*,
presumably the only reason חכמים *Chachamim* are saying is don't make a
new ברכה *berachah* is because it's the case of having a סעודה
*se'udah*. So again it proves against רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* that everybody
basically says that if it weren't
for this סעודה
*se'udah* you would have to make a new ברכה *berachah*. And the
גמרא'ס *Gemara's* answer is no.
The
חכמים *Chachamim* would might say you never, if רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
is to tell you, is that the חכמים *Chachamim* would say you
never have to make, even if it's no bread. Why did we
mention the bread? To tell you even with the bread, רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* is always going to require a new ברכה *berachah*. I
don't know if that helped at all. Yeah. Okay. Yes. So, the
people you leave behind, they don't have to actually sit eating, right?
They just be sitting there? Presumably. But you know, if they're eating
let's say, then other people join in, then oh who knows. Let's
keep on reading. תניא כוותיה *tanya kevasei*, yeah. I was just, I
just find it peculiar that, that you have a קולא
*kulla* position so to
speak, but you say you do not have to make a ברכה
למפריע *berachah lemafreia* or לכתחילה lechatchila *lechatchilah* when it's the so to
speak more serious requirement of saying ברכת המזון birkat hamazon *birchas hamazon*.
Yes, as opposed to having a snack which requires you to say
ברכות brachot *berachos*. So you've got sort of a, what's to my
mind, more of a, it's ironic that the, the bread case, right,
the heavier obligation has a קולא *kulla* position. Right, but that's I
think the logic is look, and you I also think it's ironic
because you would say that if it's something about a fixed place,
then a different place is more obviously something different, it's more breaking
with that fixed place. But the argument seems to be that when
you're having bread and when you're having a סעודה *se'udah*, that's somehow
defines everything in terms of it. So it makes everything, it's more
linked to that original eating and it's not seen in terms of
קולא *kulla* or חומרא *chumra*. Yes. There's also where היסח הדעת *hesech
hadaas*, right? If you're having coffee and you leave, well, the הלכה
halachic *halacha* is more מחמיר *machmir*, you have to say the ברכה
*berachah*, even if it's not, you don't have to return necessarily. Right.
It's more מחמיר *machmir* whereas it's a קולא *kulla* position with the
דברים הטעונים ברכה במקומן *devarim hate'unim berachah bimkomam*. Right. What's-his-name? It could
be playing cards. That's היסח הדעת *hesech hadaas*. Right, and of course
you have היסח הדעת *hesech hadaas* with coffee, but you're not necessarily.
Right, right. I do think that exactly ties in, meaning psychologically as
well, because the סעודה *se'udah* makes you always more connected to that.
Exactly. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, that yes,
we have this case of the סעודה *se'udah*, which fits, that the
חכמים *Chachamim* say you don't make a new ברכה *berachah*, רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* says you do. So that in a way falls out
to the debate of רב הונא *Rav Huna* and רב ששת *Rav
Sheshet* with a סעודה *se'udah*, can you infer from this that without
a סעודה *se'udah* everybody says you make a new ברכה *berachah*? No,
maybe we said a סעודה *se'udah* to tell you how far רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* goes, that רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* always even with
a סעודה *se'udah*. Maybe the חכמים *Chachamim*, who knows, maybe they would
be like רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. Okay, תניא כוותיה דרב חסדא *tanya
kevasei deRav Chisda*, we taught like רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*. חברים chaverim?
שהיו מסובין לשתות יין yayin ועקרו רגליהם וחזרו *chaverim shehayu mesubin lishtos
yayin v'akru ragleihem v'chazaru*, exactly this case, אין צריכים לברך *ein tzrichim
levarech*.
So you do not have to make a ברכה *berachah*, it
says it without qualification,
without the רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. Now again, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
might say that's always true. But at least רב חסדא *Rav
Chisda* would emphasize the עקרו רגליהם akru ragleihem, *akru ragleihem*. It's true
because they were קובע סעודה *koveia se'udah*. And when they return therefore
they do not have to. There's a big debate in the ראשונים
*Rishonim* how do we פסקן pasken *pasken*. Although the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
seems to be weighing in the end towards רב הונא *Rav Huna*,
the רי"ף *Rif* פסקנ'ס *paskens* like רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*, so there's
a whole debate whether in the end, we certainly don't פסקן *pasken*
like רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. But some ראשונים *Rishonim* say always שינוי
מקום
shinui makom *shinnuy makom*.
Okay, I wanted to point out one thing about
this עקרו רגליהם לילך akru ragleihem leilech. or two things about עקרו
רגליהם לילך. Why does it mention all of these mitzvot בית הכנסת
beit haknesset and חתן choson וכלה? So the בעל המאור Baal HaMaor
and the ראב"ד Ra'avad both say that it's telling you that you
need that, that normally you shouldn't be interrupting your meal, meaning not
just out of an etiquette thing, but presumably because of these issues
about ברכות brachot. and so on. You know, that if it was
a דבר רשות, dvar reshut, then finish your meal and bentch before
you go off to doing these types of things rather than interrupting
it. You interrupt, you might not come back, it'll be ברכה questions,
you'll forget to make the ברכה אחרונה. bracha achrona. But we allow
you to do it לכתחילה when it's this דבר מצוה. dvar mitzvah.
That's what the ראב"ד Ra'avad
and בעל המאור Baal
HaMaor says, not in the גמרא, Gemara. but that's what they say.
But there's another interesting question about this idea לילך לבית הכנסת. leilech
leveit haknesset.
Take a look at תוספות Tosafot and this does come up sometimes.
עקרו רגליהם לילך לבית הכנסת. akru ragleihem leilech leveit haknesset.
תוספות Tosafot says מכאן משמע שאם שכח להתפלל ונזכר באמצע סעודה mikan
mashma she'im shachach lehitpalel venizkar be'emtza seuda (never happens to me) ויתפלל
שאין צריך ברכה אפילו לכתחילה. veyitpalel she'ein tzarich bracha afilu lechatchila. There
you are, you're eating and all of a sudden you remember, "Oh
my god, I didn't daven Mincha and it's going to be Shkiah
in five minutes." Okay, so you get up and you daven Mincha
at home. Do you have to now, is that like עקרו רגליהם,
right, and to go to the בית הכנסת? beit haknesset? And now
would you have to make a, assuming we פסקן like רב ששת,
let's say you weren't having bread, would that be considered an interruption
and you would have to make a new ברכה? So תוספות Tosafot
says it says that שאין צריך ברכה אפילו לכתחילה. she'ein tzarich bracha
afilu lechatchila. Why? Because it says עקרו רגליהם לילך לבית הכנסת, akru
ragleihem leilech leveit haknesset, that there was a שינוי מקום shinui makom.
involved. But just the act of davening itself would not be an
interruption. Okay, and then he quotes another גמרא Gemara that might contradict
and then he says that גמרא Gemara is not a proof. So
תוספות Tosafot actually says that if you have to interrupt a meal
and daven, not go to shul to daven, but daven in the
place, the act of davening is not a הפסק. hefsek. It's only
because you were עוקר oker the מקום, makom, that created the issue
of שינוי מקום. shinui makom, Okay, so I thought I'd raise that
because that is something that at least that I know does come
up from time to time. Back in those days they go to
the bathroom and because they had to go do a whole thing...
Right, that's an interesting point. You know, again, I assume that that
raises a good question about the context of שינוי מקום, shinui makom
because you could argue the other point as well. שינוי מקום shinui
makom in itself, you know, maybe that gets to sort of the
issue about intention. שינוי מקום shinui makom in itself when it constitutes
a new activity, when the שינוי מקום shinui makom constitutes a continuation
of the same activity, you're going to the bathroom like a necessary
part of things that come up right during the meal. You know,
we gave the scenario: you're at a wedding in a smorg and
you're going to different places and you go to the terrace and
you walk outdoors. Right, so I think that's a good question, right,
which is that how does other things such as context and intention,
you know, define מקום makom or define the underlying phenomenon? Yeah, absolutely,
absolutely, yes. So I think you're absolutely correct about that, yeah. In
technical terms חברים? chaverim Oh, I think it's anybody, yeah. I don't
think that it's, yeah, I don't get any sense that it's the
classic חבר. chaver. Because they were מסובים? mesubim? Yeah, it's a good
question. I don't know, I mean it just it gives, you know,
you could also say why did it say that they went לקראת
חתן וכלה likrat chatan vekallah if you ignore the ראב"ד? Ra'avad? I
think it's trying to just create a realistic scenario, but I do
not treat חברים chaverim, as too technical. They are categorized as בני
חבורה, benei chaburah, חברים, chaverim yeah. Okay, so let now we would
hear when have בני חבורה. benei chaburah. Let's take a look at
that case. תנו רבנן בני חבורה. tanu rabanan benei chaburah. But you
know Rifka is correct in reminding us that the word חבורה chaburah
and חברים chaverim can definitely have a technical sense about these people,
group of people that was like this elite group that would only
eat their חולין בטהרה chulin betaharah and there would be a whole
question, be very careful about not letting outsiders eat together with them.
So when we are talking a lot about eating, so it does
raise an interesting question, you know, and in the and in the
Tannaitic literature, the issues of the חבורה chaburah are much more of
a concern than they are later like in the גמרא. Gemara's So
and all of these ברייתות, braitot, I hadn't thought about that, but
all these ברייתות braitot that refer to חברים and בני חבורה, benei
chaburah, are they being used somewhat like imprecisely to refer to just
some a similar phenomenon of people of a group or are they
being technical? I wouldn't know why they would have to be technical,
but it's important to remember that model of
חבורה chaburah that it exists. It's nice because the intentionality of eating
together in טהרה taharah and טומאה tumah right, gets
transposed perhaps at a certain point into intentionality of saying ברכות. brachot
Oh, that's an interesting idea, using that model and now talking about
how it the reality is created through ברכות brachos, that certain sense
of cohesion and intentionality. That's a very nice idea. Religious people when
they went from one place to another always had to be thinking
about טומאה וטהרה. tumah vetaharah. Yeah, שינוי מקום shinuy makom maybe is
a bigger issue. That's a good point too. Who knows? You could
make that sounds like a paper right there. The whole, that's the
whole basis of שינוי מקום shinui makom is rooted in these concerns
of טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. Who knows? תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: בני
חבורה שהיו מסובין, b'nei chaburah she-hayu mesubin, so people of a group
or חבורה chaburah that were reclining and eating, וקדש עליהם היום, v'kiddesh
aleihem hayom, and then it became the day got sanctified, which meant
it was Friday and it became Shabbat. מביאים לו כוס של יין
ואומר עליו קדושת היום והשני אומר עליו ברכת המזון, meivi'im lo kos
shel yayin v'omer alav kiddushat hayom v'hasheni omer alav birkat hamazon, דברי
רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehudah. So Rabbi Yehudah says you have to
interrupt your meal.
You stop eating now and you have to say ברכת המזון birkat
hamazon, and kiddush. The second, the second כוס, kos, okay?
So, but Rabbi Yehudah says something a little bit surprising. You would
have thought that first you do ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon you finish
up the day, then you do kiddush. Now there is a question
of the גרסא girsa of this ברייתא. Some גרסאות girsot have that
with Rabbi Yehudah, first you do ברכת המזון birkat hamazon. then you
do kiddush. Our גרסא girsa is first you do kiddush, then you
do ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon, What is the reason?
We'll get to using one כוס kos for both in a minute,
but the second
כוס kos for ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon, what is the reason for
that order? So תוספות Tosfos says the reason would be because you
can't if you make ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon again, they're doing it,
they're talking about taking a כוס kos of wine, they're assuming that
ברכת המזון birkat hamazon is על הכוס. al hakos. But if you
make ברכת המזון על הכוס Birkat Hamazon al hakos and it now
became dark and it became Friday night, and you're making ברכת המזון
birkat hamazon from your Friday meal על הכוס, al hakos what problem
are you going to have when you're done with ברכת המזון? birkat
hamazon? How can you drink from the כוס? kos? It's already Friday
night and I can't drink from the כוס kos without making kiddush.
So therefore you have to make kiddush first, although it's ironic, and
then wrap up the previous meal so you can drink from the
כוס kos of ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon. That's, what? You want to
incorporate this as your? No, no, this is Rabbi Yehudah. Rabbi Yehudah
wants you to be done with your Friday meal and start your
Shabbat meal, but because you have to do ברכת המזון על הכוס
Birkat Hamazon al hakos. according to תוספות, Tosfos, you have to do
kiddush first. The בעל המאור, Baal Hamaor, somebody else says, I think,
I forget, that no, that since the thing that forced you to
say ברכת המזון birkat hamazon was the kiddush, was the new day,
you start with that,
that was in a sense the interruption or the pause of the
ברכת המזון birkat hamazon and it's followed by the ברכת המזון. birkat
hamazon But that's a stranger idea. תוספות Tosfos basically says it's just
a technical need of being able to say ברכת המזון על הכוס.
Birkat Hamazon al hakos? Now, of course it is strange because the
whole idea for Rabbi Yehudah was to create an interruption. So תוספות
Tosfos says that's why before you do the kiddush you'll be מסלק
השולחן. mesallek hashulchan.
That was discussed before, right, about the סילוק השולחן. silluk hashulchan. Fine,
you remove the table, that created the division, that created the break.
But now in terms of the ברכות, brachos we have to for
technical reasons do kiddush first. That's the position of Rabbi Yehudah. רבי
יוסי אומר אוכל והולך עד שתחשך. Rabbi Yosi omer ochel v'holech ad
she-techeshach. Here's the Rabbi Yosi we know, keep on eating until it
gets dark. Now, what do you do when you're done eating according
to Rabbi Yosi? Okay, you also have to bench and now make
kiddush. What order do you do? So גמרו, gamru, you finish your
meal, כוס ראשון מברך עליו ברכת המזון והשני קדושת היום. kos rishon
mevarech alav birkat hamazon v'hasheni kiddushat hayom. Now it's very the order
makes sense, right? You do ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon. you wrap it
up, and then you do קדושת היום. kiddushat hayom. Of course according
to Rabbi Yosi, you know, it's not exactly clear why he doesn't
have Rabbi Yehudah's concern, because one does wonder, right, although I was
allowed to continue eating my meal after it got dark, that's because
it was a continuation of the previous meal. It was still considered
a weekday meal.
Now that I'm benching and I'm
saying it על הכוס, al hakos, right, after now that I'm done
with my meal, maybe I should have the same concern that I
can't eat until I make kiddush. So it is a little bit
interesting, right, that Rabbi Yosi, is that clear? Meaning what the reality
for Rabbi Yosi when you're done with your meal is not clear
why it is so different than the reality for Rabbi Yehudah. You're
done with your meal, you have to do ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon
you have to make kiddush, maybe even though Rabbi Yosi let me
eat when it got dark, that was when it was part of
the meal, now that I have benched, maybe I should have to
do kiddush before I can drink the wine of ברכת המזון. birkat
hamazon, But apparently not, and apparently again, maybe still, you know, we
already allowed you to be eating, so even the wine of the
ברכת המזון birkat hamazon, will maybe be considered a continuation of that,
and he lets you do the normal order. You do ברכת המזון
birkat hamazon. and then you do kiddush. Now, everybody points out, this
isn't the way this isn't relevant for us because we פוסקין פורס
מפה ומקדש. pasken poreis mappah umekaddesh. I wanted to use this opportunity
before we continue the גמרא Gemara though, because I was reminding myself
of the הלכות halachos about the פורס מפה ומקדש. poreis mappah umekaddesh.
So it's interesting. Everybody agrees if you have the פורס מפה ומקדש,
poreis mappah umekaddesh, as we said this could happen on Purim let's
say, it could happen other times, it could happen let's say Purim
and you're having your meal and you're having wine, and then you
have to do פורס מפה ומקדש. poreis mappah umekaddesh. What do you
do in terms of בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen and in
terms of המוציא? So everybody agrees you do not make a new
בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri HaGafen. It's very strange. You will actually
make kiddush without בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri HaGafen. You'll start kiddush,
you say the thing before, or you just start, you know, with
the ברכה after בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri HaGafen, אשר קדשנו במצותיו
ורצה בנו. Asher Kideshanu B'Mitzvotav V'Ratzah Banu. etcetera, so imagine making the
קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush* without the בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen, *Borei
Pri Hagafen*, just jumping right in. Because בורא פרי הגפן borei pri
hagafen *Borei Pri Hagafen* is not technically a ברכה *Beracha* of the
קידוש Kiddush *Kiddush*, it's incorporated into the קידוש kiddush *Kiddush* because you
need it in order to make קידוש kiddush על היין *Kiddush Al
HaYayin* and you're going to need it to drink the wine. But
since you've already been drinking wine, if it's a פורים סעודה *Purim
Seudah*, or סתם *stam* for, if you've been drinking wine, and this
is immediately following without interruption, it doesn't need a new בורא פרי
הגפן borei pri hagafen *Borei Pri Hagafen*. So some would suggest what,
that the בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen *Borei Pri Hagafen* is
part of קידוש kiddush *Kiddush*? Yeah, I know, it is true, if
you have to make it for somebody else, so you'd have to
say when it's needed it becomes part of קידוש kiddush *Kiddush*, but
when it's not needed, it's not needed, it's true. But that is,
but yes, you do have both of those הלכות *halachot* that when
you do have to make it, you can make it for somebody
and it's not just a ברכת הנהנין *Birkat HaNehenin*. But if that's,
but if it's not needed at all, you actually would make, and
this is, this is להלכה *L'Halacha*, you make קידוש kiddush, *Kiddush* without
בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen *Borei Pri Hagafen*. Now, do you
make המוציא *Hamotzi*? Do you say בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen
*Borei Pri Hagafen* and then do you just take off the thing
and jump into the bread, or do you have to make now
a new המוציא *Hamotzi*? So here there's a big debate in ראשונים
*Rishonim*, because some say no, the act of קידוש kiddush. *Kiddush*, right,
קידוש kiddush, *Kiddush* that didn't need בורא פרי הגפן borei pri hagafen,
*Borei Pri Hagafen*, you were still in the middle of eating and
you could drink the wine, but the act of קידוש kiddush *Kiddush*
now that you have made the קידוש *Kiddush*, that now says that
this is a new meal, as a new meal, sort of like
the שינוי מקום *shinui makom*, even though you're sitting at the table
and all the food is there, as a new meal it needs
a new המוציא *Hamotzi*. And others disagree, it's a yes, it's become
a שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* meal, but without an interruption and it doesn't
need a new המוציא *Hamotzi*. So the שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* brings
both opinions, the משנה ברורה *Mishnah Berurah* says ספק ברכות brachos להקל
*safek berachot l'hakel*, you don't make a המוציא *Hamotzi*. So it would
be fascinating in this case, you would actually go ahead and make
קידוש *Kiddush* without בורא פרי הגפן *Borei Pri Hagafen* and then have
the שתי לחם *Shtei Lechem* and uncover the שתי לחם *Shtei Lechem*
and eat them without a המוציא *Hamotzi*. So it'd be a fun
thing to do on a פורים *Purim* Friday in order to have
that experience of living that הלכה *halacha*. This, I've not been to
one, but this שול shul, *shul* when פורים *Purim* falls out on
Friday does have late afternoon סעודות *seudahs*. Ah, so I wonder, if
you know what they do, I assume they do that directly. They
have the whole issue of דאווענינג *davening* and stuff like that. But
so you wouldn't make בורא פרי הגפן *Borei Pri Hagafen*, you're saying
only because presumably you would have been... if it's a פורים סעודה
*Purim Seudah*, I assume you've been drinking wine. What if you've been
drinking alcohol not wine? Well, that's a problem because פורים סעודה *Purim
Seudah* requires wine, I mean the definition of the whole issue of
חייב לבסומי *chayav l'vsumei* and משתה *mishteh* and so on. Okay, anyway,
let's go on. So now we have this debate, so now we've
known the debate of רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי יוסי *Rabbi
Yosi*, but now we're also seeing that they're debating or they're discussing
what to do with the ברכות berachos. *berachot*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this: אמאי *Ammai*? Why is it that you need
Michael's question, two כוסות kosos, *kosot*? ונימרינהו לתרוייהו אחדא כסא *Vinimrinhu l'travaihu
achada kassa*? Say both ברכת המזון birkat hamazon *Birkat HaMazon* and קידוש
*Kiddush* on the same כוס kos, *kos*. Now תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says
this is only according to רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*, even though both
רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* and רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* have two ברכות
*berachot*. Because according to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* the whole point is
is that the ברכת המזון birkat hamazon *Birkat HaMazon* was to end
the previous thing and the קידוש *Kiddush* was to start the new
thing and the whole idea was to separate them, so there's no
way you're going to use one כוס kos *kos* to do them
both, the whole point is to separate. Okay, but according to רבי
יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* he says actually according to רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*
you need to combine them. Why? Because remember תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot* asks
the question, according to רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*, how do you have
קידוש במקום סעודה *Kiddush Bimkom Seudah* if you're done with all your
eating and then you're making קידוש *Kiddush*? And how do you have,
what meal is your first סעודת שבת Shabbos *Seudah Shabbos* if presumably
you're not eating a new meal now that you're done with all
your eating? So he says according to רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* once
you've made קידוש *Kiddush* after the סעודה *Seudah*, that defines it as
קידוש במקום סעודה *Kiddush Bimkom Seudah* and that retroactively also defines what
you've been eating as סעודת שבת Shabbos *Seudah Shabbos*. Okay, that's תוספות
Tosafot, *Tosafot*'s חידוש *chiddush* that according to רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* his
explanation, the קידוש *Kiddush* comes after and works together with the סעודה
*Seudah*, which might also explain why רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* allows you
to do ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon? *Birkat HaMazon* first, because it's all
one thing, it's not these two separated things like תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*.
So if that's true, make ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon *Birkat HaMazon* and
קידוש *Kiddush* with the same כוס kos *kos*. The whole point is
that you're incorporating the קידוש *Kiddush* afterwards into the meal. So use
the same כוס kos *kos*. So why not use the same כוס
kos *kos*? So אמר רב הונא אמר רב ששת *Amar Rav Huna
Amar Rav Sheshet*: אין אומרים שתי קדושות על כוס אחד Kos echad
*Ein Omrim Shtei Kedushot Al Kos Echad*. You don't do two sanctifications,
obviously one is a ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon, *Birkat HaMazon*, but on
the same כוס kos. *kos*. Okay, so you can't have, you have
to have two כוסות kosos. *kosot* under a חופה chuppah *chuppah*? We're,
I'll talk about that in a minute. I'll talk about that in
a minute, one minute. מאי טעמא *Mai Ta'ama*, why not? אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק *Amar Rav Nachman Bar Yitzchak*: לפי שאין עושים מצוות
חבילות חבילות mitzvos chavilos chavilos, *Lefi SheEin Osim Mitzvot Chavilot Chavilot*. You
don't bundle up your מצוות *mitzvot*. The way the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*
explains it, you don't want it to seem like it's a burden.
Like oh good, let's reuse this and do double duty with this
כוס kos, *kos*. So don't use your לולב *lulav* to burn the
חמץ *chametz*? Yeah, it's a question, but each one deserves, right, because
that's once one מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* was done, do another מצוה *mitzvah*
with it. Yeah, it's a good point, I mean you are correct,
that's a slightly, but but here I would reframe it as the
whole idea of קידוש על הכוס al hakos *Kiddush Al HaKos* and
ברכת המזון על הכוס Birkat Hamazon al hakos *Birkat HaMazon Al HaKos*.
If you say something על הכוס, al hakos. it gives weight and
significance to this ritual act. I mean, just think about it, by
the way, I don't know if people are aware, but according to
the גמרא Gemara you do not say שבע ברכות Sheva Brachos על
הכוס, al hakos, you do not say ברכת אירוסין Birkat Erusin על
הכוס, al hakos, you do not do ברכת ברית מילה Birkat Bris
Milah על הכוס. al hakos, All of that act came later. And
I think that we, if we were, if we would not do
those things על הכוס, al hakos. they would not have the same,
you know, religious impact. Doing it על הכוס al hakos, gives a
lot of weight and makes it, you know, makes it into a
ritual, gives it a lot of significance. What? It looks religious. Exactly.
And gives it this significance. So I would argue this, you know,
this idea in general אין עושין מצוות חבילות חבילות ein osin mitzvos
chavilos chavilos comes up in other contexts. But for here in particular,
you want to give, if you want to give weight to this
ברכה, you don't want to reuse some other כוס, kos which actually
anyway, you know, it's like also defines it not in its own
terms. So this was a כוס ברכת המזון kos Birkat Hamazon used
for this. So is this a קידוש or is this a ברכת
המזון? Birkat Hamazon So I think particularly in the context of קידוש
where the whole idea is that the כוס kos, is giving weight
and the כוס kos is connected to the identity, you don't want
to double up and muddy the waters. Okay, so that's the גמרא's
Gemara answer. Let's continue a little bit and then I'll talk about
the חופה chuppah. question. ולא, Velo, do you not do that? והתניא,
Vahatanya, it was taught in a ברייתא: הנכנס לביתו במוצאי שבת, Hanichnas
leveiso b'motza'ei Shabbos, מברך על היין ועל המאור ועל הבשמים. mevarech al
hayayin v'al hamaor v'al habesamim. You come home on מוצאי שבת, motza'ei
Shabbos, so this is, this is הבדלה, Havdalah, right? יין מאור בשמים.
Yayin maor besamim. We do יין בשמים מאור. yayin besamim maor. We'll
talk about that order later. ואחר כך אומר הבדלה. V'achar kach omer
Havdalah. Okay, so that's your normal הבדלה Havdalah על הכוס. al hakos
ואם אין לו אלא כוס אחד, Ve'im ein lo ela kos echad,
now let's say you only have one cup of wine and you
need it for ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon. because you've also been eating.
So what do you do? ואם אין לו אלא כוס אחד, Ve'im
ein lo ela kos echad, מניחו לאחר המזון. manicho l'achar hamazon. So
the כוס kos you were going to use for ברכת המזון, Birkat
Hamazon let's say you're, you know, for your שלש סעודות, Shalosh Seudos,
so you leave it till after you're done eating. Wait, what's the
case? I thought you came to your house. So that's a good
question, right. So it could be you came to your house. I'll
discuss that, but for now we're assuming we're talking about a different
scenario. Not you came home from שול, shul, but you were at
home, you were eating, you were having שלש סעודות, Shalosh Seudos, and
you only have one כוס kos. of wine. Do you use it
for, do you use it for בענטשן, bentching, do you use it
for הבדלה? Havdalah? What are you going to do? The issue is
the physical cup or the quantity? No, no, no, the amount of
wine, the amount of wine. כוס kos. אחד is a way of
saying one cup's worth of wine. Right. Okay, so what do you
do? One minute. So what do you do? מניחו לאחר המזון, Manicho
l'achar hamazon, you use it for בענטשן, bentching, and you set it
aside, ומשלשלן כולן לאחריו, umeshalshelan kulan l'acharyo, and you say all of
the ברכות afterwards. משלשל, Meshalshel, the word like, like, like well, no,
like a שלשלת, shalsheles, like a chain. Right. You string all, you
daisy-chain all of the ברכות on it. So basically you see what
you're doing here is you're saying ברכת המזון birchas hamazon and הבדלה
Havdalah all on the same כוס. kos So you see you can
bundle up. גמרא says no, אינו דומה. eino domeh. No, if you
don't have, if you only have one כוס, kos we'll give you
a little latitude, but when you have two כוסות, kosos? you should
use separate כוסות. kosos. That's where you only had one. Now Michael
asks a question. Michael said, why do we switch scenarios? We talk
about coming home and then we talk about you're sitting and you're
eating and you need a כוס for ברכת המזון. birchas hamazon, I
mean, if you came home after שול, shul. don't eat until you
make הבדלה. Havdalah. So some say אי הכי נמי, ei hachi nami,
we're talking about a different scenario. תוספות Tosafos, says no, because here's
the thing: you only have one כוס, you came home from שול.
shul. Now we know you're not allowed to eat before הבדלה. Havdalah.
But you're planning tonight to have your סעודה and if you're poor,
you know, if a guy only has one כוס of wine he's
probably pretty poor. So the main part of your meal is going
to be your bread. Okay, so you're already planning in advance and
you're saying to yourself, if I go ahead and make הבדלה Havdalah
now על הכוס, al hakos. I'm not going to have a כוס
יין kos yayin for when I later want to eat my sandwich.
So we will allow you, to תוספות, Tosafos to have your meal
before הבדלה, Havdalah, even though you're not allowed to normally eat before
הבדלה, Havdalah, in order to enable you to do a ברכת המזון
על הכוס Birkat Hamazon al hakos, and to wrap it up with
הבדלה Havdalah because you only have one cup of wine. Which is
pretty amazing. Like my first response reading that תוספות, Tosafos so don't
have bread, have something else. Okay, but that wasn't so much of
an option, especially if you were poor. But my second point is,
you know, so don't make ברכת המזון על הכוס. Birkat Hamazon al
hakos, Okay, since when do we normally have ברכת המזון birchas hamazon.
על הכוס? al hakos, Maybe if you have ten people and you
happen to have some wine around, but clearly in the גמרא you
see from all the cases we're reading, that the, you know, everybody
says, what do you do when you're מפסיק, mafsik, you make ברכת
המזון birchas hamazon על הכוס al hakos. and you make this על
הכוס. al hakos The assumption is you're always making ברכת המזון birchas
hamazon על הכוס, presumably even if you're alone, even a יחיד, yachid,
even by yourself. The גמרא like takes that completely for granted. So
in order to allow you to have your sandwich and to do
ברכת המזון birchas hamazon, על הכוס, תוספות Tosafos, says we'll allow you
to eat before הבדלה. Havdalah. So although this is still done in
some שולס shuls when they have this ברכת המזון birchas hamazon for
שלש סעודות, Shalosh Seudos, they do it על הכוס and then they
use the same כוס for הבדלה Havdalah even when there's gallons of
grape juice around. Right, so there is, I mean which is against
the idea of אין עושין מצוות חבילות חבילות. ein osin mitzvos chavilos
chavilos. Yeah, that idea definitely is brought out and as Michael says,
well once you did one מצוה you know with it. I do
another מצוה *mitzvah* with it. Let's, you know, let's hold off on
that, okay? I'll get back to you on that, but you are
right that that's not just the case about אין לו שנים *ein
lo shnayim*. That really becomes like an idea to use the same
כוס *kos* for doing both. No, but wouldn't, you know, this taken
for granted when we do ברכת המזון birchas hamazon *Birkat Hamazon* on
a כוס *kos*, how come the popular custom is not... Okay, that's
different. That's, there are other גמרות *Gemaras* and more in ברכות *Brachot*
that talk about the different practices about ברכת המזון *Birkat Hamazon* on
a כוס *kos*. But certainly the גמרא *Gemara* assumes we're always doing
it. Now, I want to read to the two dots and then
I want also discuss the case of the of the חופה chuppah,
*chuppah*. The גמרא *Gemara* says, that we're still saying now you don't
use the same כוס *kos* for two, although Charlie correctly reminds us
that we often דוקא davka *davka* do that in a case of
סעודה שלישית *Seudah Shlishit* and הבדלה havdalah *Havdalah*. Now, והאי יום טוב
Yom Tov *v'hai yom tov*, but here's another question. יום טוב Yom
Tov שחל להיות אחר שבת shechol lihyos achar Shabbos. *Yom Tov she'chal
lihyot achar Shabbat*. If יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* comes after
שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat*, right? So we had יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom
Tov* before שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* this holiday season, but if יום טוב
Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* came after שבת shabbos *Shabbat*, then you're going
to make a הבדלה havdalah *Havdalah* and קידוש *Kiddush* at the same
time, because you only make הבדלה havdalah *Havdalah* from a יום טוב
Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* שבת shabbos, *Shabbat* juxtaposition when יום טוב Yom
Tov *Yom Tov* follows שבת *Shabbat* because יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom
Tov* is a lesser קדושה kedusha *kedusha*. And הבדלה havdalah. *Havdalah* is
always from a higher קדושה kedusha. *kedusha* to a non-קדושה kedusha *kedusha*
or a lesser קדושה *kedusha*. So you'll never make it from יום
טוב yom tov. *Yom Tov* into שבת *Shabbat*, but you'll make it
from שבת *Shabbat* into יום טוב yom tov, *Yom Tov*. So שבת
*Shabbat* and then יום טוב *Yom Tov*, יום טוב *Yom Tov* is
Sunday, you'll make הבדלה havdalah *Havdalah*, but you'll also have to make
קידוש *Kiddush* for יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So how are you going
to like incorporate, or what order are you going to do these
things? So let's take a look. ויום טוב שחל להיות אחר שבת
*v'Yom Tov she'chal lihyot achar Shabbat*. יום טוב *Yom Tov* comes after
שבת *Shabbat*, דאית ליה *d'is lei*, obviously in that case you have
two cups of wine. Now, why is it obvious you have two
cups of wine? Says תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*, well look, it's one thing
to say by הבדלה havdalah *Havdalah* time you've had a, you know,
you've really enjoyed your שבת *Shabbat* and you're left to your last
cup of wine. This actually happens, you know, sometimes it's הבדלה havdalah.
*Havdalah* and we have no wine or grape juice left by the
end of שבת *Shabbat* just anyway. Okay. But at the beginning of,
you know, it's יום טוב *Yom Tov*, anyway, יום טוב *Yom Tov*
is a time where it's supposed to be, you know, אך שמח
*ach sameach* and you have whatever, presumably it's the beginning of a
יום טוב *Yom Tov*, you're going to have your wine store will
still be good, so you know, your stocks. So therefore presumably you
have two cups of wine. ואמר רב *v'amar Rav*, and רב *Rav*
says, יקנ״ה *Yakneh*. So you do יין *yayin*, קידוש *kiddush*, נר ner,
*ner*, הבדלה havdalah. *havdalah*. The order you do it is יין *yayin*
and קידוש *kiddush*, קידוש *kiddush* comes first, and הבדלה havdalah. *havdalah* afterwards.
Again, that's ironic. It's sort of like קידוש *kiddush* before ברכת המזון
*Birkat Hamazon*, when do you first want to end the previous one
and start the new one? So we'll talk about that in a
minute. But the point though being is you use the same כוס
*kos* for קידוש *kiddush* as you do for הבדלה havdalah. *Havdalah*. So
don't you see you use one כוס *kos* for two things, for
two separate ברכות *brachot*? So אמרי מדלא אמר זמן zman, *amri midlo
amar zman*, so let's figure out what scenario we're talking about. Why
did רב *Rav* not talking about זמן zman, *zman*? שהחיינו shehecheyanu. *Shehecheyanu*,
right? You say שהחיינו shehecheyanu *shehecheyanu* when you say קידוש *kiddush*. So
what is the only קידוש *kiddush* of יום טוב *Yom Tov* you
make without a שהחיינו *shehecheyanu*? The only time you make קידוש *kiddush*
on יום טוב *Yom Tov* without a שהחיינו *shehecheyanu*. שביעי של פסח
Shvii shel Pesach. *Shvii shel Pesach*, right? שמיני עצרת *Shmini Atzeret* is
a חג בפני עצמו *chag bifnei atzmo*, so you make שהחיינו *shehecheyanu*,
right? You make a שהחיינו *shehecheyanu* on both days of יום טוב
*Yom Tov*, beginning and end, because of the ספק יומא *safek yoma*.
So the only time you don't, שביעי של פסח *Shvii shel Pesach*,
that's seen as a continuation. So why didn't he mention זמן *zman*?
מכלל דבשביעי של פסח עסקינן *mikhlal d'vishvii shel Pesach askinan*. We're talking
about שביעי של פסח *Shvii shel Pesach*. So in that case, the
end of פסח *Pesach*, דכל מה דהוה ליה אכליה ולית ליה *d'chol
ma d'havei lei achlei v'leis lei*. So that's the case, it's the
end of פסח *Pesach*. Yeah, you're done with, you've eaten up all
of your פסחדיק *Pesach-dik* products, you drank all your wine, yeah, that's
also a scenario of having only one cup of wine. Which is
a pretty weak answer. Okay, but anyway, but גמרא *Gemara* says because
nevertheless like presumably רב *Rav* is giving you a general ruling. So
גמרא *Gemara* says fine, I'll give you another case. יום טוב ראשון
*Yom Tov rishon* דאית ליה *d'is lei*. How about first day of
יום טוב *Yom Tov*? Or even שמיני עצרת *Shmini Atzeret*. A day
that you're, where you obviously that day you'll have, you know, it's
a new יום טוב *Yom Tov*, you're going to have a lot
of wine. ואמר אביי *v'amar Abaye*, and there we also see they're
discussing the order. יקזנ״ה *Yakznah*. ורב אמר יקנה״ז yaknahaz, *v'Rav amar Yaknehaz*.
Okay, this is going to be fun, fun. So אביי *Abaye* says
when you have to do a הבדלה havdalah *Havdalah* and קידוש *Kiddush*
and and a שהחיינו *shehecheyanu*, right? It's anything other than שביעי של
פסח *Shvii shel Pesach*, in that case you do יין *yayin*, קידוש
*kiddush*, זמן *zman*, which is classic קידוש *kiddush*, you do the whole
קידוש *kiddush*, and then you do the הבדלה havdalah *havdalah*, נר ner?
*ner*, הבדלה havdala *havdalah*. Why there's no בשמים besamim. *besamim* I'll talk
about in a minute. So אביי *Abaye* makes a lot of sense,
at least I mean you would want הבדלה *havdalah* first, but anyway,
do the full קידוש *kiddush* and then do the הבדלה *havdalah*. ורב
אמר יקנה״ז *v'Rav amar Yaknehaz*, which is actually how we rule. יין
*yayin*, קידוש *kiddush*, נר ner *ner*, הבדלה *havdalah*, and you do שהחיינו
*shehecheyanu* at the very end, which is strange. But regardless, what you
see is that it's a beginning of יום טוב *Yom Tov*, you're
saying שהחיינו *shehecheyanu*, presumably you have two cups of wine, and we're
still incorporating it all on the same כוס *kos*. So you see
it's the exact opposite of what you said. Not to need separate
ones, but quite the opposite, the assumption that you're going to do
it all on the same כוס *kos*. So what's the story? Separate
כוסות kosos *kosot* or the same כוס *kos*? Says the גמרא *Gemara*,
אלא *ela* here's the answer. הבדלה וקידוש חדא מילתא היא *Havdalah v'kiddush
chada milta hi*. הבדלה *Havdalah* and קידוש *kiddush* are the same thing.
Now, they're the same in the fact that they're like diametrically opposite!
But they're doing the same idea. They're distinguishing, they're distinguishing from holy
and non-holy in different directions, okay? But ultimately they're defining the nature
of the day and distinguishing it from the previous days. So in
that case, even though one is working from before and one is
working going forward, nevertheless, they're both about defining the nature of the
day and you can therefore incorporate them all in the same cup.
But ברכת המזון וקידוש תרי מילי נינהו, benching and Kiddush, those are
conceptually completely different things or completely unrelated, they're from different universes. One
is about sanctifying and defining the day, and the other has to
do with the fact that you ate a meal. So therefore it
would be inappropriate to use the same cup for both. Now this
gets to this issue about reusing or not, because here you see
in the case of יקנה״ז, not only are we allowing it, presumably
we're even saying you should do it. Bundle it up. The problem
is that when it's conceptually a very different type of a thing,
then each one loses its identity if you try to smush them
together. Right? If you try to combine a ברכת המזון cup with
a Kiddush cup, you don't know what you have here. It loses
its identity. But if it retains its identity, then maybe you're allowed
or even required to bundle them up. Okay, so that's where we
stop for now. We're going to get to in a minute or
tomorrow the issue of the order יין קידוש נר הבדלה, yayin kiddush
ner havdalah, but I want to talk about this issue of חבילות
חבילות chavilos chavilos in terms of the חופה. chuppah, So if you
take a look here at תוספות, Tosfos שאין עושין שתי קדושות על
כוס אחד, she'ein osin shtei kedushos al kos echad, תוספות Tosfos says,
ויש נוהגים בחופה, veyesh nohagim bachuppah, some have the practice in a
חופה, chuppah. מטעם זה, mita’am zeh, שלא לומר שבע ברכות על כוס
ברכת המזון. shelo lomar sheva berachos al kos birchas hamazon. Now, he's
not talking about under the חופה, chuppah, he means the meal after
the חופה. chuppah. Okay? That you don't say the שבע ברכות sheva
berachos on the cup of wine, because under the חופה, chuppah, the
כוס יין kos yayin is all about the שבע ברכות, sheva berachos,
but at the meal, the כוס יין kos yayin technically is about
the ברכת המזון, even for people who normally wouldn't have a כוס
יין kos yayin for ברכת המזון. So that would be bundling two
separate things together, ברכת המזון and שבע ברכות. sheva berachos. אלא מביאין
כוס אחר, ela mevi'in kos acher, ואין מברכין על השני בורא פרי
הגפן. ve'ein mevorchin al hasheni borei pri hagafen. So the first one
you do בורא פרי הגפן, but not the second, כיון שכבר בירך
על כוס ברכת המזון, keivan shekevar beirech al kos birchas hamazon, אין
נכון לברך פעמים, ein nachon livarech pe'amayim, you shouldn't make a בורא
פרי הגפן twice. Now, it's interesting because mostly this is what we
do. Right? Did everybody ever see like the whole magic they do
with the two כוסות? kosos It's basically all because of this. I'm
the one leading benching, I say, right, I don't say בורא פרי
הגפן yet, I want that to sort of come at the end.
It's interesting, תוספות Tosfos has כבר בירך בורא פרי הגפן. kevar beirech
borei pri hagafen. It sounds like תוספות, and which makes sense, I
just finished benching, I'll say בורא פרי הגפן right now. Okay? So
we say the בורא פרי הגפן later, but okay, I'm going to
say בורא פרי הגפן on this, then we do, take this cup
around, everybody says their thing, da-da-da-da-da-da, bring it back, I'm going to
use my cup to say בורא פרי הגפן, that's the cup of
benching, this is the cup of שבע ברכות, sheva berachos, and then
we do the whole magic. It's really not such a magic. Basically,
everybody wants, you want to get everybody, the guy who's making the
benching and the חתן כלה chosson kallah to have from both כוסות.
So you pour from these two into a third, that's now the
mix of the two, and from the third back into these two,
so every cup has from the two cups. That's that whole magic
of what you pour the whole thing. Anyway, that's all of that.
Anyway, that's all based on this of מצוות חבילות חבילות, you don't
want to bundle them up. Okay. Now תוספות says, אך רבינו משולם
היה אומר הכל על כוס אחד. ach rabbeinu meshullam hayah omer hakol
al kos echad. He didn't do this whole thing. He would do
it all on one cup. דלא דמי לברכת המזון וקידוש דתרי מילי
נינהו. dilo dami lebirchas hamazon vekiddush desrei milei ninhu. For the case
that we're dealing with, a weekday meal saying the ברכת המזון and
the Kiddush, okay, those are separate things, כדאמרינן בסמוך. ke'amarinan besamuch. והכא
חדא מילתא היא. vehacha chada milsa hi. דברכת המזון גורם לברכת נישואין.
debirchas hamazon gorem lebirchas nissuin. Why are you doing שבע ברכות? sheva
berachos? You're doing שבע ברכות sheva berachos because you're having a meal.
So because the שבע ברכות sheva berachos are connected to the meal
and are coming as a result of the meal and according to
some maybe were even established as part of the ברכת המזון, that's
why you're doing it. So it actually these are very integrally connected
and you can use one cup, maybe you even should use one
cup. So that's an interesting debate. We don't do that, but that's
a very persuasive position. Now he talks about ברכת אירוסין birchas eirusin
under the חופה. chuppah, וברכת אירוסין ונישואין, uvirchas eirusin venissuin, when we
do it under the חופה, chuppah. נהגו לומר על שתי כוסות. nahagu
lomar al shtei kosos. You do it on two separate cups. הטעם
דהרגילים זה בלא זה, hata'am dehorgilim zeh belo zeh, because often they
would come separate, כדאמרינן בכתובות, ke'amarinan bichesuvos, מברכין ברכת אירוסין בבית אירוסין
וברכת חתנים בבית חתן. mevorchin birchas haeirusin bevevs eirusin uvirchas chasanim bevevs
chosan. Okay, so it used to be that they would come separate
times of the year, you would have אירוסין eirusin a year before
and different locations, the house of the חתן or the house of
the father-in-law, and therefore these are although they are conceptually related, by
God they're all about getting married and they're all coming at the
same time, nevertheless, in their origins they are very distinct types of
ברכות. ועוד דנהגו לקרות כתובה בין תרוייהו, ve'od denahagu likros kesuvah bein
tarveihu, והוי הפסק, vehovei hefsek, ולכך נתכוונו. ulchach niskuvnu. When you make
the כתובה, kesuvah, it's דווקא davka in order to like sort of
like the whole שינוי מקום idea to make a break and to
say that this is something different. ולכך נתכוונו, ulchach niskuvnu, ולכן צריך
שתי כוסות. ulachen tzarich shtei kosos. You can't use the argument of
using one cup. that it's all sort of, you know, it's all
doing the same thing right now. So תוספות says when he,
so he says this conceptually is distinct and it's interesting though, this
מנהג minhag of writing the כתובה ketubah because you could have still
have said, okay, but I used it, who cares? I used it
a week ago for אירוסין eirusin and I'll use it now for
נישואין. nissu'in. It's fundamentally the same thing. So you see according to
תוספות when you are allowed to bundle them and when it is
even when it's conceptually and thematically linked, it it needs to be
in the same experience. You need to be doing them as it
were all at the same time, like in one event. If you're
doing them at separate events, that by itself requires a separate כוס.
Now, very often now, I think because people are just afraid about
spilling and whatnot, what I see most of the time is that
they just slightly refill the כוס. Okay, because you have to anyway,
if you drink from it you can't use the כוס unless you
add wine. It's considered פגום. pagum. But at least the practice mostly
I see is people do not have two כוסות under the חופה,
probably because you don't need to get another thing to trip and
make a mess and be concerned about. But maybe some, maybe some
still do. Okay, but this is the issue about when do you
דוקא davka combine, when do you דוקא davka separate, and I do
want to get back to Charlie's question. I'll get back to you
tomorrow about like why we דוקא do combine ברכת המזון with שבע
ברכות sheva brachos when strictly speaking in the גמרא you shouldn't. If
you want to, let's just start very briefly this next discussion about
the יקנה"ז. Yaknahaz. Okay, so let's take a look. We're going to
have like five different positions here about how to incorporate, oh
my God, okay, how to incorporate these things. Which is very compelling
to really urge two כוסות under the חופה.
Yeah, I find it, you find it compelling?
Okay. Yeah, I do.
It resonates. Okay, I find it more resonates to have only one
כוס during the שבע ברכות sheva brachos meal for
the inspiration I heard about the הבדלה aspect and the ברכת המזון
for the bringing the קדושה of שבת into the week. But the
question again is how does it
reconcile itself with the הלכה discussion here. Let's read just briefly these
opinions and then we'll continue this tomorrow. גופא, gufa, יום טוב שחל
להיות אחר שבת. יום טוב is after שבת and you have to
do בנץ' bench and you have to do הבדלה and קידוש all
together, and with זמן, with שהחיינו. Or well, no, actually forget it.
We'll do it with the שהחיינו part later. Without זמן, שביעי של
פסח. רב אמר יקנ"ה, Rav amar Yaknah, יין קידוש נר הבדלה. yayin
kiddush ner havdalah. As we said, by itself good, יין and קידוש
by itself and then הבדלה by itself. The only question is why
קידוש before הבדלה. So you know the רשב"ם Rashbam, just says that
if you take a look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam רב אמר יקנ"ה,
Rav amar Yaknah, סבירא ליה קדושת היום עדיפא מהבדלה. svira lei kidushas
hayom adifa mehavdalah. If you want to emphasize one, you'd rather emphasize
the holiness of the day you're going into rather than the, you
know, rather than the fact that you're leaving a קדושה. So you
want to sort of, you know, focus on that even though chronologically
it's out of order. אי נמי דכי מבדיל ברישא מיחזי דהוי קדושת
היום כמשאוי. ee nami dechi mavdil bereisha michzi dahavei kidushas hayom kemasoi.
This is an idea we have very often that when you have
orders of things, you should do הבדלה later because you want to
show like when you on חנוכה Chanukah you do הבדלה in שול.
So obviously you wait until שבת is out, but first you light
נר חנוכה ner Chanukah and then you do the הבדלה. Although that's
ironic, you can't light נר חנוכה ner Chanukah while it's still שבת,
but nevertheless you want to show how you're reluctant
to do the הבדלה. So even if it's just a minute, you
push it off a little bit to demonstrate that reluctance. Again ironic,
because you're already doing the קדושה which is in a way introducing
the next day but ending שבת
and introducing the next day. Right. Anyway, so that's רב. רב says
קידוש comes before הבדלה. ושמואל אמר ינה"ק. u'Shmuel amar Yanhak. So שמואל
Shmuel says, no, I gotta tell you, I like שמואל Shmuel better.
You know יין נר הבדלה. yayin ner havdalah. You do the full
הבדלה. Again, oh, I forgot to mention why no בשמים. besamim. And
then you do the קידוש, thank you. So you do הבדלה and
then קידוש. Okay, and now we're going to see tomorrow about five
more possibilities. You can actually, you know, figure out how many logical
possibilities. Right? What is it? If there's four of them, it's four
times three times two, there's 24 logical possibilities. We're only going to
have about six or seven of them. Anyway, but why, I want
to end by saying why nobody is talking about בשמים. besamim So
the רשב"ם says with no בשמים besamim because because because you have
a נשמה יתירה neshama yesaira also on יום טוב. And therefore you
don't need בשמים besamim because the whole idea of בשמים besamim is
you lose your נשמה יתירה neshama yesaira and you need the בשמים
besamim. to revive you. And that's why you don't do it. תוספות
says no, that can't be because if the same idea of נשמה
יתירה neshama yesaira applied on יום טוב, then every הבדלה from מוצאי
יום טוב motei Yom Tov you should have to use בשמים. besamim
So it's not that you have a נשמה יתירה, neshama yesaira, this
idea on יום טוב. But you do have, you do have שמחה
simcha of יום טוב. And the שמחה simcha of יום טוב is
enough to sort of support you with that loss of the נשמה
יתירה neshama yesaira so you don't need the בשמים besamim. to do
that function. The fact that you're entering into the שמחה simcha of
יום טוב gives you enough sort of חיזוק, chizuk, you know, gives
you enough revival that you don't need the בשמים. besamim And that's
why we do not have... The בשמים besamim when we go from
in this scenario when we go from שבת to יום טוב. We
make קידוש, we make נר, ner but why do you make נר?
ner Because נר is about fire and creativity, I can discuss נר
a little bit more, but anyway, נר is allowed on יום טוב,
not allowed on שבת, so that is a clear, you know, divider.
But בשמים besamim. is not needed and therefore we don't have בשמים.
So right now we have the debate of רב and שמואל. Shmuel.
רב says you do the קידוש part first, שמואל Shmuel says you
do the הבדלה part first. We will see more positions about this
tomorrow.